准备好了吗  孩子们
Are you ready, kids?
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
我听不见
I can't hear you
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
是谁住在深海的大菠萝里
Who lives in a pineapple under the sea?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
方方黄黄伸缩自如
Absorbent and yellow and porous is he
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
如果四处探险是你的愿望
If nautical nonsense be something you wish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
那就敲敲甲板让大鱼开路
Then drop on the deck and flop like a fish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
准备
Ready
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
冬眠预备周
导演
分镜
翻译: 1440kHz
编剧
动画总监
创意总监
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
特约音乐制作
好了
There we go
德克萨斯
海绵宝宝  我把树叶都扫成一堆了
Hey, Spongebob, I got all the leaves raked--
海绵宝宝  这边怎么还有树叶
Spongebob, what are all these leaves doing here?
你不是要扫起来的吗
You said you were gonna rake 'em?
我在扫了
I am raking the leaves
可地上还是到处都有树叶
But they're still all over the ground
珊迪  我最多就只能扫这么快了
Sandy, I can't rake any faster
这些可是大树叶
These are big leaves
而且还会没完没了裂成不少小树叶
And they keep breaking in to more leaves
没事干就去给盐砖抛光什么的
Then go scrape the salt lick or something
趁还来得及把事情都解决了
We gotta get this stuff done before it's too late
这到底是在急什么  珊迪
What's the big rush anyway, Sandy?
都跟你说了  海绵宝宝
I told you, Spongebob
我下周冬眠
I'm hibernating next week
冬眠
Hibernating?
什么意思
What's that?
我一整个冬天都要睡觉
It's when I go to sleep for the whole winter
我也会那样吗
Can I do that?
不会  傻瓜
No, silly
哺乳动物才会冬眠
It's a mammalian thing
珊迪  你可能没注意到
Sandy, you may not have noticed
我正是百分百的哺乳动物
but I is 100% mammal
别闲聊了  海绵宝宝
Enough chitter-chatter, Spongebob
时间不多了
We don't have much time left
为什么  珊迪
Why, Sandy?
那你这个
When does your
渗碳作用
carburation
[ carburation（渗碳作用）
与 hibernation（冬眠）谐音 ]
啥时候开始
begin?
一周过后
In one week
可是珊迪  那样就只剩
But Sandy, that only gives us--
一二三
one, two, three--
168个小时可以一起玩了
168 more hours of play time--
你说得对
You're telling me
还有不少事没做
And there's still so much to do
要去攀岩
We gotta climb some things
攀岩
Climb
要去蹦极
We gotta jump off of stuff
蹦极
Jump
要去骑行
We gotta ride
骑行
Ride
我还不想睡
I don't want to go to sleep yet
等等  珊迪
Wait, Sandy
我睡觉期间可燃烧不了体内的碳水
I can't burn carbs in my sleep
珊迪
Sandy?
怎么
What?
珊迪  我愿意为你献出
Sandy, I'm willing to sacrifice
我还没出卖给蟹老板的任何时间
any of my time
that I haven't already sold to Mr. Krabs to you
这就好  海绵宝宝
Well, I'm glad, Spongebob
因为之后这七天
Because for the seven days
就只有你我
it's going to be you, me
还有这俩吸汗头带在一起
and these sweat bands
沙山
我可以解释
I can explain
我热血沸腾得不得了啊
I'm hotter than a hickory smoked sausage
也许要是我们唱了歌
Maybe, if we sing that song
它就能活过来了
he'll come to life
好了吗
Ready?
从前有个沙人
Oh, there once was a sand man--
生活想怎么极限就怎么极限
Life's as extreme as you want to make it
也许我们唱错了
Maybe we didn't sing it right
好
Yeah
好大的运动量
What a workout
我明天一定还会有这种感觉
I'm gonna be feeling this tomorrow
你真是太出彩了  海绵宝宝
I gotta say I'm impressed with you, Spongebob
冬眠预备周有你在就是好得不得了
You're making this the best pre-hibernation week ever
我得先回家了  免得小蜗又咬烂沙发
Well, I'd better get home
before Gary chews up the sofa again
晚安  小蜗
Goodnight, Gary
一大早清爽游个泳最棒了
Nothing like a refreshing morning dip
对吧  海绵宝宝
huh, Spongebob?
睡一半干嘛要起来
What happened to sleeping?
我一整个冬天都要睡
Well, I'll be asleep all winter
只剩三天时间可以玩了
we only got three days for fun
动作快
Well, hurry now
巨蚌就喜欢在这种时候进食
The giant clams like to feed at this hour
是不是很棒
Isn't this great?
确实  从没玩过这么极限的捡针游戏
Yeah, I've never played extreme jacks before
[ 捡针游戏：抛一颗球
在球落地前捡起尽可能多的针 ]
好  海绵宝宝
OK, Spongebob
这次一定特有趣
this one's gonna be fun
咱俩拿着巨型挖耳棒对打
We just whack each other with these giant ear cleaners
谁掉下去谁就输
till one of us falls off
各就各位  预备
On your mark, get set--
珊迪  你确定应该要
Sandy, are you sure we're supposed
站在这上面吗
to be standing up here?
开始
Go
海底针
快点  海绵宝宝
Come on, Spongebob
我们去工园骑双人自行车
We're going for a tandem ride through the park
一听就很安全
Gee, that sounds safe--
我是说  有趣
I mean, fun
行  我准备好了
OK, I'm ready
不是说好要去公园骑车吗  珊迪
I thought you said
we were riding through the park, Sandy
确实  海绵宝宝
I did, Spongebob
去工业园
The industrial park
真本事就得在这使
This is where the real action is
踏板使劲踩
Come on, pedal
这段特别要技术
This part gets pretty technical
骑到高速跑道了
Now for the speed course
撑着点
Hang on
希望能成
I hope we make it
我玩得也很开心
I'm having fun too
快醒醒  慢乌龟
Wake up, slowpoke
要去空中钓鱼了
We're going fly fishing
这只松鼠想杀了我
This squirrel's trying to kill me
再玩这种危险动作
Any more of these stunts
我就要化为一滩死水了
and I'll be reduced to a puddle
等下  一定要想办法找借口脱身
Wait a minute, I gotta talk my way out of this
珊迪  我得跟你说个事
Sandy, I think I need to tell you something
什么事
What is it?
就只是我感觉有点
Well, it's just that I'm feeling sort of--
我感觉很需要
I just feel like maybe I need to--
你先等着  海绵宝宝
Hold that thought, Spongebob
现在来整点我在南方乡下老家的最爱
cause it's time for a down-home favourite
进针堆找干草
find the hay in the needle stack
找到了吗
Did you find it?
还没
Not yet
我就到这边找
Well, I'm going to look over here
你找吧
You do that
找到了  海绵宝宝
Found it, Spongebob
快来  三局两胜
Come on, best two out of three
躲起来
Gotta hide
家里
Home?
不行  小蜗会说漏嘴
No, Gary can't keep a secret
石头底下
Under a rock
太有创意了
It's so original
海绵宝宝
Spongebob
你在哪  小方块
Where are you, little square dude?
海绵宝宝的领带
Spongebob's tie
还有他身上其他衣服
and all his other little dressings
可
But--
可他都会先叠好衣服
But he always folds his clothes
然后才会到处裸奔
before running around in the nude
他一定是出事了
Something terrible must've happened to him
蟹堡王
你们大家都听好了
All right, listen up, y'all
我就此召集搜索队
I'm rounding up a search party
海绵宝宝失踪了
Spongebob's gone missing
救生艇就位
Man the lifeboats
阿尔法小队  搜索住宅区
Alpha team, you search uptown
黄金小队  搜索市中心
Gold team searches downtown
大家谁有异议
Any questions?
黄金小队最强
Gold team rules
动作快
Now get moving
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
寻人启事
来人找那边
Someone look up there
都给我卖力点
Put your dorsal fins into it
加把劲  他有可能就在硫磺泉某处
Come on, he can be anywhere in these sulphur fields
海绵宝宝
Hey, Spongebob
起码我气质还在
Well, at least I still have my personality
到潮湿洞穴里面找
Check in this here moist cave
海绵宝宝
Spongebob
报告情况
Status report
他不在毒海胆湾
He's not in the poison sea urchin cove
再去找
Well, look again
他不在水蛭养殖场
He's not at the leech farm
再去找
Well, look again
他不在我脑海里
He's not in my thoughts
再去想
Well, think again
全裤头村请注意
Attention, Bikini Bottom
现在必须双倍
the time has come to double
不对  三倍努力去找
no, triple our efforts
能不能休息一下
How about a break?
都已经找好几天了
We've been at it for days
考虑一下小朋友吧
Think about the children
好办法
That's a good idea
让小朋友爬进一般人进不去的小地方
Use the children to crawl into small places
you couldn't normally reach
全是一派胡言
This is a load of barnacles
我都听见了
I heard that
没找到海绵宝宝  谁都不准走
No one's going anywhere till we find Spongebob
等等
Wait, uh
他在这
here he is
那不是海绵宝宝
That ain't Spongebob
海绵宝宝是方的
Spongebob is square
我准备好了  我准备好了
I'm ready, I'm ready
才没有
No, you ain't
找到方块宝宝了
I found Squarebob
海草哥
那只是个麦片盒
That's just a cereal box
并且他是黄的
Besides, he's yellow
他就在这
Yeah, here he is
我能回去了吗
Could I go home now
快看  他就在天上
Oh, look, he's up in the sky
他没
He's not--
他们一定再去找了
They must've gone to search some more
海绵宝宝  你在哪
Spongebob, where are you?
在下面吗
You under there?
没有
Nope
我可以解释
I can explain
海绵宝宝
Spongebob?
没有
Nope
海绵宝宝  你在哪
Spongebob, where are you?
没有
Nope
那只松鼠疯了
That squirrel's gone crazy
但她一定不会去找石头底下
But she'll never look under a rock
确实
You said it
珊迪找不到我们的
Sandy'll never find us
等等  你们不明白
Wait, you don't understand
快看  是我海绵宝宝
Oh, look, it is I, Spongebob
就在空地上
out here in the open
海绵宝宝
Spongebob?
拜托  放我进去
Come on, let me back in
你们不明白
You don't understand
海绵宝宝  我都担心死了
Oh, Spongebob, I was so worried
还以为你出了什么事
I thought something terrible happened
快点
Come on
还有时间可以去粉碎原子呢
There's just enough time to go atom smashing
珊迪  等等
Sandy, wait
没空再等了
There's no time to wait
要冬眠了
Hibernation
珊迪  一定要抽空
Sandy, you gotta make time
这可是大事
This is important
我是男子汉
I am a man
好  珊迪
OK, Sandy
我
I--
我没法再跟你玩了
I can't play with you anymore
我受不了你玩的游戏
I just can't take the games
都快把我撕碎了
They're tearing me apart
我全坦白了
There I said it
答应我继续当朋友吧
Now, just promise we can still be friends
拜托  珊迪
Please, Sandy
这真的很难开口
this isn't easy
我
I--
珊迪
Sandy?
从来没想过会说这种话
I never thought I'd say it
感谢海神王她冬眠了
but thank Neptune for hibernation
你们都是谁啊
Who are you people?
罪犯生活
分镜总监
翻译: 1440kHz
分镜
编剧
动画总监
创意总监
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
蟹堡王
现在回到甲壳类犯罪剧场
And now back to the Crustacean Crime Theatre
站住  小偷
Stop, thief
他往哪跑了
Which way did he go?
往那跑了
He went that way
快抓住他
Let's get him boys
该死  又失败了
Curses, foiled again
那家伙实在太坏了
What a no good eel in the kelp that guy was
小偷就是最坏的坏蛋
There ain't nothing worse than a thief
就该把小偷关一辈子
Thieves need to be locked up forever
把鳃都吊起来  绞死他们
They should all be strung up by their gills
强迫他们呼吸空气
and forced to breathe air
可蟹老板  那你偷的东西怎么说
But, Mr. Krabs, what about all the stuff you stole?
你什么意思
What do you mean?
比如说那个桶
Like that barrel
咸海农场所有
上面写  咸海农场所有
It says property of Salty Sea Farms
我腌椰菜都是到那租的
That's where I rent me pickles from
原来桶也是租来的吗
Are you renting the barrel too?
那个  不是
Well, no
那就是你买的了
Then you bought it?
不是
No
那样不就是偷了吗
Then isn't that stealing?
那个  我
Well, I, uh--
那这条热泉桑拿的毛巾怎么说
What about this towel from the Sizzling Spring Sauna?
热泉桑拿
那是
Well, that's--
还有比基尼贝尔电话
And this Bikini Bell phone?
那个  我
Well, I--
还有珊迪的灌木剪
And Sandy's hedge clippers?
那是
They're um--
还有痞老板的割草机
And Plankton's lawnmower?
他是
Well, he--
连泡芙老师的卷发器你都有
Even Mrs Puff's hair curlers?
是人家送的
That one was a gift
听好了  那些都是
Listen, all that stuff is, uh
借来的
borrowed
Borrowed?
这下就放心了
Well, that's a relief
还以为你没经过允许就拿了
I thought you took it without permission
要什么允许啊
Permission, shmermission
东西想什么时候借就什么时候借
You can borrow anything you want, anytime
趁人家没发现东西丢了  还回去就行
as long as you get it back before it's missed
人尽皆知的事情  对吧
Everyone knows that, right?
好
OK
那就行
All right, then
抱抱
Hugs
你们今天干活可努力了
you put in a hard day's work, boys
可我没在这上班
But I don't work here
再见
See you later
差点就露馅了
That was close one
你今天想干什么
What do you want to do today?
不知道
I don't know
你今天想干什么
What do you want to do today?
不知道  你今天想干什么
I don't know, what do you want to do today?
不知道
I don't know
你今天想干什么
What do you want to do today?
不知道
I don't know
你今天想干什么
What do you want to do today?
气球
我知道今天想干什么了
I know what I want to do today
我要来点钱
I need some money
我没钱
I don't have any money
海绵宝宝  我特别特别想要气球
Spongebob, I want a balloon really, really badly
特别特别想要
Really, really badly
没事的  派大星
It's OK, Patrick
海绵宝宝第一国家银行有不少钱
There's lots of money
in the First National Bank of Spongebob
跟我来
Follow me
我也破产了
I'm broke too
也许可以找章鱼哥借钱
Maybe we can borrow money from Squidward
等等  与其借钱
Wait, instead of borrowing the money
不如就直接借气球好不好
why don't we just borrow the balloon?
好
Yeah
跟蟹老板一个样
Like Mr. Krabs
就单纯是借一下  对吧
It's just borrowing, right?
对  借一下不会有事
Yeah, and borrowing is OK
只要能还回去就行  对吧
as long as we bring it back, right?
对
Right
实在太棒了
This is so great
一定可以玩得特开心
We're gonna have so much fun
可以先拿着气球到处跑
First, we can run with the balloon
对  然后可以拿着气球去海滩
Yeah, then we could go to the beach with the balloon
对  然后可以拿着气球骑自行车
Yeah, then we could take a bike ride with the balloon
然后能去看电影
Then we could go to the movies
打电玩
and the arcade
溜个冰
and the ice rink
买披萨
and the pizza shop
上月球
And the moon
上天
and the sky
再上垃圾箱后边的车
and then a car behind the dumpster
再去糖果店
And the candy shop
再去我后院
And then my backyard
再上飞机
And then in a plane
爬石头顶上
And over a rock
爬山底下
And under a hill
陪着大鲸鱼
And with a whale
我们喜欢借
We love borrowing
爆了
It popped
现在该怎么还回去  海绵宝宝
How are we gonna return it now, Spongebob?
我有碎片
I've got the pieces
我有气
I got the air
快  把碎片拼起来
Hurry, put the pieces on
我们让气球爆了
We popped the balloon
还不回去了
We can't return it
我们是小偷
We're thieves
必须去自首
We have to confess
自首
Confess?
你什么毛病
Are you out of your mind?
知不知道上面会怎么处置我们这种人
Do you have any idea what they do to people like us?
我们这可不是搞什么诈骗邮件
We're not talking about some dumb mail fraud scheme
或者是搞劫持
or hijacking here
我们偷了个气球
we stole a balloon
上面要把我们关起来一辈子
And they're going lock us up forever
你说得对
You're right
保持头脑清醒
We've just got to keep our heads
表现正常点
Act normal
是卖艺的
Street performers
没用
It's not working
气球
你们好
Hi, there
不要免费气球吗
Don't you want a free balloon?
今天是全国免费气球节
It's national free balloon day
他发现我们了
He's on to us
裤头村再也不安全了
It's not safe in Bikini Bottom anymore
动作一定要快  隐藏好行踪
We've gotta move fast and cover our tracks
这就来  海绵宝宝
I'm on it, Spongebob
最后再看一眼吧  派大星
Take a last look, Patrick
再也回不去了
We can never go back
再见  裤头村
Goodbye, Bikini Bottom
我们路途中只有彼此
We've only got ourselves
还有背负的行囊和罪责
and what we can carry on our backs
对
Yup
得轻装上阵才行
We're gonna have to travel lighter
我想回家
I want to go home
家回不了  派大星
We can never go home, Pat
我们是通缉犯
We're wanted men
余生只能在四散奔逃中度过
We'll spend the rest of our lives running, running
不过起码坐在火边很暖和
But at least it's warm around the fire
如果是在海底  那怎么会有
If we're underwater, how can there be a--
我好怕  海绵宝宝
I'm scared, Spongebob
没有暖呼呼的床
No more nice warm beds
没有蟹黄堡
No more Krabby Patties
没有邮件收得到
No more getting mail
没有小蜗
No more Gary
没有电影
No more movies
没有章鱼哥
No more Squidward
没珊迪  没珍珍
No more Sandy, or Pearl
没蟹老板
or Mr. Krabs
什么都没了
No more anything
我要冰淇淋
I want ice cream
不过处境也不算太难堪  对吧
But it doesn't have to be all bad, right?
起码我们还有彼此
I mean, at least we have each other
对
Yeah
而且逃跑还能锻炼臀部还有大腿
And all that running is good for your buns and thighs
对吧
right?
对  臀部还有大腿
Yeah, buns and thighs
还可以受冷
And the bitter cold?
十分清爽宜人
It's bracing, isn't it?
没错  当罪犯可能确实很有趣
Yeah, maybe being a felon can be fun
可以解开领带
We can loosen our ties
没错
Yeah
可以自由飞翔
And we could fly
没错
Yeah
好吧  飞不起来
OK, we still can't do that
不过也用不着刮毛了
But we don't have to shave
早就想到了  兄弟
I'm way ahead of you, buddy
还可以讲话硬气点
And you get to talk tough
这里一城不容我们二虎
This town ain't big enough for the two of us
我来试试
Let me try
混账
Hey, punk
最棒的一点就是
And the best part is
既然我们是罪犯了
now that we're felons
借到的东西就不用还回去了
we don't have to return anything we borrow
好耶
Yeah
然后全都要怪你
And we owe it all to you
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
拿气球的邪恶计划是你想出来的
Taking the balloon was your evil plan
我光说不做
I'm nothing but a lot of talk
真正下毒手的是你
You're the one with the sticky fingers
派大星  你这坏榜样最好了
Patrick, you're the best bad influence ever
你也是
You, too
希望有东西可以吃
I wish we had something to eat though
看我身上有什么
Look what I've got
长方形
Rectangles
这可不是普通的长方形  是巧克力棒
Not just any rectangles, candy bars
巧克力棒
得把巧克力棒留着当后半辈子的干粮
All we have to do is make 'em last the rest of our lives
谢了  海绵宝宝
Thanks, Spongebob
我现在就吃了吧
I think I'll eat it now
我巧克力棒哪去了
Where'd my candy bar go?
一定是丢了
I must've dropped it
你刚吃了  派大星
You just ate it, Pat
吃得满脸都是
It's all over your face
跑哪去了
Where'd it go?
我都快饿死了
I'm going to starve
跑哪去了
Where'd it go?
找不到
I can't find it
会在什么地方
Where could it possibly be?
咋了
What?
你偷了我巧克力棒
You stole my candy bar
我没偷
No, I didn't
原来是这样啊
So that's how it is, huh?
一朝当小偷  终生当小偷
Once a thief, always a thief
你把你那条吃了
You ate yours
这条是我的
This is mine
你把我唯一的干粮吃了
You took my only food
现在我要挨饿了
Now I'm gonna starve
给  派大星
Here, Patrick
我分我的一半给你
just take half of mine
你的
Yours?
你说的是我的
You mean mine
你还要不要了
Do you want it or what?
除非你承认是你偷的  否则我不要
I don't want it unless you admit you took it
这可是我的巧克力棒
This is my candy bar
骗子骗子  我招枯梓
Liar, liar, plants for hire
是火烧裤子  派大星
It's pants on fire, Patrick
你当然知道了  骗子
Well, you would know, liar
要是你非要那样
Well, if you're gonna be that way
我就自个吃了
I'll eat it myself
不准你吃
You better not
我警告你
I'm warning you
不准
Don't
住口
Stop it
不准
Don't
你就一神经病
You're a crazy person
自打你偷那气球  我就该料到了的
I should've expected this
after the way you stole that balloon
是吗  派大星
Did I, Patrick?
是吗
Did I?
会不会是你的犯罪头脑催眠我去偷的
Or did your criminal mind hypnotise me to steal it?
够了
That's it
先是气球
First, the balloon
现在又是我巧克力棒
Now, my candy bar
你都失控了
You're out of control
我
I--
我要告发你
I'm telling on you
等我先告发你再说
Not if I tell on you first
我会比你先到
I'll beat you there
你就要有麻烦了
You're gonna get in trouble
你才有
No, you are
警察局
可以为你们做什么
What can I do for you boys?
我们偷了个气球
We stole a balloon
出了什么事
What's the problem here?
看来是这两位偷了个气球
Well, it appears these two stole a balloon
你们会怎么处置我们
What are you going to do to us?
好  跟我来
OK, follow me
要是坐不了牢  就别犯罪
If you can't do the time, don't do the crime
好  刑期满了
OK, time's up
出去吧
Now, get out
可
But--
可我们偷了个气球
but we stole a balloon
对啊  这天可是免费气球节
Yeah, on free balloon day
你们路上要不要吃点棒棒糖
How about some lollipops for the road, boys?
来发誓再也不会不经允许借东西了
Let's vow never to borrow anything
without permission again
我同意
You said it
好啊  你们哪个警察偷了我棒棒糖
All right, which one of you flatfoots stole my lollipop?
这可真是
Oh, brother
我认真的
I mean it